So far, we've created the contract that
will define what the database looks like
for the rest of the application, but we
haven't really created the database yet.
To do that, we need to create
a new class known as DB Helper.
Because we will be using SQLite as our
database, we'll extend the Android class
SQLiteOpenHelper to
create our DB Helper.
SQLiteOpenHelper exists mainly to take
care of creating the database for
the first time and
upgrading it when the schema changes.
The DB Helper also provides other
classes with a reference to
the database, giving them a way to
access it's information through queries.
SQLiteOpenHelper provides us with
two important methods, onCreate and
onUpgrade.
OnCreate is responsible for
creating the actual database for
the first time,
while OnUpgrade is responsible for
making sure the database
schema is up to date.
We'll be overriding both OnCreate and
OnUpgrade in our DB Helper class.
In exercise two, create the database,
open up WaitListDBHelper.java,
and modify the class declaration
to extend SQLiteOpenHelper.
Inside the DBHelper class,
create a final string called
DATABASE_NAME to specify
the database file name.
Let's call it waitlist.db.
This will be the name of a local file
on the Android device that will store
all our data.
Then, create another final
integer to store the current
database version number.
This should always start from one and
any time you decide to modify the data
base schema in your code,
you should increment it.
This will force users to upgrade their
databases whenever you release a new
version of the app.
Also, don't forget to
change the contract if you
ever do change the database schema.
The constructor shouldn't do anything
special here, so let's just simply call
the parent's constructor and let the
parent class handle everything for us.
To call the parent constructor,
call super and pass through the context,
which is usually the calling activity,
the database name, and
the version number.
This null argument is supposed to be
something called a cursor factory, but
we won't be using one in the scope of
this app, so let's just pass null.
Now it's time to override
the onCreate method that will
actually create the database
file when called.
Start by writing the SQL statement that
will describe the database schema.
Remember to follow the contract that
we created in the previous exercise.
An SQL create table statement
starts with create table,
followed by the table name and
the table description.
That is a comma-separated list of each
column name followed by its type,
all in a set of parentheses.
Here is what our SQL create
statement should look like.
The ID column is our primary
key with auto-increment,
meaning that it should generate it's own
values each time we insert a new row.
The guest name is just a text
field that can not be null.
The party size is an integer
that is also not null.
Finally, the time stamp field
is of type time stamp, and
the default value is timestamp,
which means the SQL database system
will automatically assign the current
time every time a new row is added.
Notice how we've used the content
strings from the contract to
programmatically generate
this SQL string.
This is because if we decide to
rename a column in the future,
we'll only need to do so
in the contract and
every time we reference that column in
the app, it'll automatically be updated.
Once we get our string variable
SQL_CREATE_WAITLIST table ready,
we can now call execSQL on our database,
passing in that string
which creates the database.
The last step is to overwrite
the OnUpgrade method.
This is only called when
the version number we defined
earlier becomes larger than the version
number of the database on the device.
It's meant to update the database
schema without losing any user data, so
ideally this should include
a schema update statement.
Since we only have one version so far
all we'll do here is drop the current
database, if it exists,
and create a fresh one.
But say later on you decide to add
a new column to the wait list table,
then you should change the version
number up here to 2 and
implement OnUpgrade with an SQL
statement that would append that
column to the database
without having to drop it.
Perfect.
If everything is done correctly,
then you should be able to pass all of
the tests that we've created for you.
Try to follow these steps yourself,
and see if you can pass all the tests.
Now you can run those tests
by doing a right-click, and
going down to Run Database Test and
when it comes up,
it will ask you which device
you want to run the test on.