In exercise four, we need to modify
the adapter even further, and instead of
just passing in the cursor account,
we need to pass the entire cursor so
that the adapter can extract
the guest information and
display it in the RecyclerView properly.
In GuestListAdapter, since we're passing
in the entire cursor, rather than just
a count, let's replace this integer with
a cursor variable called mCursor, and
then modify the constructor to accept
a new cursor, rather than an integer.
And inside, set the local
mCursor to be equal to cursor.
And then finally, update the
getItemCount to return the getCount from
the passed in cursor object.
Now, for the part where we bind
the cursor data with the UI, just like
a typical recycler view adapter, we
will override the onBindViewHolder, and
inside, by the data, the specified
position to the viewHolder passed in.
But before we do that,
let's have a quick look at what
the result of a query looks like.
A result of any selection
query is formed as a table,
if you select everything
from a database table, and
the result table is
identical to that table.
A result of any selection
query is formatted as a table.
If you select everything, for example,
then the result is identical
to that database table.
You can think of the cursor as
if it's pointing to a particular
row in that result.
To extract information from a particular
row, you can move the cursor to point
there, and then extract
the specific goal information.
For example,
to get the guest name in the fourth row,
move the cursor to the fourth position,
and
then call getString,
passing in the index of that column.
To do so in the onBindViewHolder,
first thing we need to do is call
the mCurser.movetoposition,
passing in the current binding position.
And this will move the cursor to the
point where we have the data that we're
interested in.
It will return false,
if there's no data there, or
if it's out of the bounds of the cursor,
so make sure you add a check, and
if it's not true, just return.
If everything's good,
then we can get the name of the guest,
and the party size from that cursor.
To get the guest's name,
use mCursor.GetString.
And then passing
the index of that column,
which you can get also using the
getColumnIndex function in the cursor,
and then just passing the column name,
which we can get from the contract.
The same can be done
to get the party size,
except that we're using the get
integer instead of the get string.
Then to reflect this information in
the UI, we just set the text for
the holder.nameTextView and
.partySizeTextView.
We've already created all the UI for
you, however,
if you're interested, check out
this activity_main.xml file, and
see how these text fields
have been created.
Now, the very last step is drop
date MainActivity, and instead of
pausing in the getCount of the cursor,
just pause in the entire cursor.
And if we run this now, voila,
we get the actual names and
party sizes for
each of our fake guests, perfect.
Now, let's start adding guests
of our own, but as always,
remember to try everything
we've done yourself.